<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Liferay Faces Portal Liferay Language Portlet Integration</title>
	<para>In a normal JSF web application, the <ns:link
			xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/util/Locale.html">Locale</ns:link> that is used to
		display internationalized values is dictated by the locale specified in the end-user's web-browser. However,
		Liferay Portal permits the user to select a different locale (language) using the Language Portlet. The user's
		choice is ultimately saved as a <ns:code>languageId</ns:code> in the Liferay <link
			xlink:href="http://docs.liferay.com/portal/5.2/javadocs/portal-service/com/liferay/portal/model/User.html"
			>User</link> object and is persisted to the database.</para>
	<figure>
		<title>Liferay Portal Language Portlet</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/liferay-language-portlet.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>In order to provide seamless integration between JSF portlets and the language selected by the user, Liferay
		Faces Portal provides the LiferayLocalePhaseListener. The listener monitors the RESTORE_VIEW phase of the JSF
		lifecycle and will automatically set the locale inside the <ns:link
			xlink:href="http://docs.oracle.com/cd/E17802_01/j2ee/javaee/javaserverfaces/2.0/docs/api/javax/faces/component/UIViewRoot.html"
			>UIViewRoot</ns:link> according to the value specified by Liferay's <link
			xlink:href="http://docs.liferay.com/portal/5.2/javadocs/portal-service/com/liferay/portal/model/User.html#getLocale()"
			>User.getLocale()</link> method, which is aware of the selected <ns:code>languageId</ns:code>. This in turn
		causes internationalization techniques such as the <link
			xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/javaee/javaserverfaces/1.2/docs/tlddocs/f/loadBundle.html"
			>f:loadBundle</link> tag and the <link xlink:href="#liferay-faces-i18n">i18n</link> EL keyword to
		automatically translate message keys into the language selected by the user with the Liferay Language
		Portlet.</para>
</chapter>
