<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Portlet Standard</title>
	<sect1 revision="1">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para> Portlets are web applications that are designed to run inside a portlet container that implements either
			the Portlet 1.0 (<link xlink:href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=168">JSR 168</link>) or Portlet 2.0
				(<link xlink:href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=286">JSR 286</link>) standard. Portlet containers
			provide a layer of abstraction over the Java EE Servlet API, and consequently require a servlet container
			like Apache Tomcat to function. The reference implementation for Portlet 1.0 and 2.0 is the Apache Pluto
			project: <link xlink:href="http://portals.apache.org/pluto">http://portals.apache.org/pluto</link>. </para>
		<para>Portals are standalone systems that use a portlet container as the runtime engine for executing portlets.
			When a portal is asked to deliver a portal page to the end-user’s web browser, each portlet is asked to
			render itself as a fragment of HTML. It is the job of the portal to aggregate these HTML fragments into a
			complete HTML document.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Portlet Lifecycle</title>
		<para>The Portlet 1.0 standard defines two lifecycle phases for the execution of a portlet that a compliant
			portlet container must support: The first is the javax.portlet.PortletRequest.RENDER_PHASE, in which the
			portlet container asks each portlet to render itself as a fragment of HTML. The second is the
			javax.portlet.PortletRequest.ACTION_PHASE, in which the portlet container invokes actions related to HTML
			form submission. When the portal receives an HTTP GET request for a portal page, the portlet container
			executes the portlet lifecycle and each of the portlets on the page undergoes the RENDER_PHASE. When the
			portal receives an HTTP POST request, the portlet container executes the portlet lifecycle and the portlet
			associated with the HTML form submission will first undergo the ACTION_PHASE before the RENDER_PHASE is
			invoked for all of the portlets on the page.</para>
		<para>The Portlet 2.0 standard adds two more lifecycle phases that define the execution of a portlet. The first
			is the javax.portlet.PortletRequest.EVENT_PHASE, in which the portlet container broadcasts events that are
			the result of an HTML form submission. During this phase, the portlet container asks each portlet to process
			events that they are interested in. The typical use case for the EVENT_PHASE is to achieve Inter-Portlet
			Communication (IPC), whereby two or more portlets on a portal page share data in some way. The other new
			phase added by the Portlet 2.0 standard is the javax.portlet.PortletRequest.RESOURCE_PHASE, in which the
			portlet container asks a specific portlet to perform resource-related processing. One typical use case for
			the RESOURCE_PHASE is for an individual portlet to process Ajax requests. Another typical use case for the
			RESOURCE_PHASE is for an individual portlet to generate non-HTML content (for download purposes) such as a
			PDF or spreadsheet document.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Portlet Modes</title>
		<para>The Portlet 1.0 and 2.0 standards define three portlet modes that a compliant portlet container must
			support: javax.portlet.PortletMode.VIEW, javax.portlet.PortletMode.EDIT, and javax.portlet.PortletMode.HELP.
			Portal vendors and portlet developers may supply custom modes as well. VIEW mode refers to the rendered
			portlet markup that is encountered by the user under normal circumstances. Perhaps a clearer name would be
			&quot;normal&quot; mode or &quot;typical&quot; mode, because the word &quot;view&quot; is also used by
			developers to review to the &quot;view&quot; concern of the MVC design pattern. EDIT mode refers to the
			rendered portlet markup that is encountered by the user when selecting custom values for portlet
			preferences. Perhaps a clearer name would be &quot;preferences&quot; mode. Finally, HELP mode refers to the
			rendered portlet markup that is encountered by the user when seeking help regarding the usage and/or
			functionality of the portlet.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Portlet VIEW Mode</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/portlet-view-mode.png" width="400px"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<figure>
			<title>Portlet EDIT Mode</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/portlet-edit-mode.png" width="400px"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<figure>
			<title>Portlet HELP Mode</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/portlet-help-mode.png" width="400px"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Portlet Window States</title>
		<para>Portals typically manifest the rendered markup of a portlet in a rectangular section of the browser known
			as a portlet window. The Portlet 1.0 and 2.0 standards define three window states that a compliant portlet
			container must support: javax.portlet.WindowState.NORMAL, javax.portlet.WindowState.MAXIMIZED, and
			javax.portlet.WindowState.MINIMIZED. The NORMAL window state refers to the way in which the portlet
			container displays the rendered markup of a portlet when it can appear on the same portal page as other
			portlets. The MAXIMIZED window state refers to the way in which the portlet container displays the rendered
			markup of a portlet when it is the only portlet on a page, or when the portlet is to be rendered more
			prominently than other portlets on a page. Finally, the MINIMIZED window state refers to the way in which
			the portlet container displays a portlet when the markup is not to be rendered.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Portlet Preferences</title>
		<para>Developers often have the requirement to provide the end-user with the ability to personalize the portlet
			behavior in some way. To meet this requirement, the Portlet 1.0 and 2.0 standards provide the ability to
			define preferences for each portlet. Preference names and default values can be defined in the
			WEB-INF/portlet.xml configuration file. Portal end-users start out interacting with the portlet user
			interface in portlet VIEW mode but can switch to portlet EDIT mode in order to select custom preference
			values.</para>
		<example>
			<title>Specifying preference names and associated default values in the WEB-INF/portlet.xml configuration
				file</title>
			<programlisting>
&lt;portlet-app&gt;
	&lt;portlet&gt;
		...
		&lt;portlet-preferences&gt;
			&lt;preference&gt;
				&lt;name&gt;datePattern&lt;/name&gt;
				&lt;value&gt;MM/dd/yyyy&lt;/value&gt;
			&lt;/preference&gt;
			&lt;preference&gt;
				&lt;name&gt;unitedStatesPhoneFormat&lt;/name&gt;
				&lt;value&gt;###-###-####&lt;/value&gt;
			&lt;/preference&gt;
		&lt;/portlet-preferences&gt;
		...
	&lt;/portlet&gt;
&lt;/portlet-app&gt; </programlisting>
		</example>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 xml:id="portlet2ipc">
		<title>Inter-Portlet Communication</title>
		<para>Inter-Portlet Communication (IPC) is a technique whereby two or more portlets on a portal page share data
			in some way. In a typical IPC use case, user interactions with one portlet affect the rendered markup of
			another portlet. The Portlet 2.0 standard provides two techniques to achieve IPC: Public Render Parameters
			and Server-Side Events.</para>
		<para>The Public Render Parameters technique provides a way for portlets to share data by setting public/shared
			parameter names in a URL controlled by the portal. While the benefit of this approach is that it is
			relatively easy to implement, the drawback is that only small amounts of data can be shared. Typically the
			kind of data that is shared is simply the value of a database primary key.</para>
		<para>The Server-Side Events technique provides a way for portlets to share data using an event-listener design.
			When using this form of IPC, the portlet container acts as broker and distributes events and payload (data)
			to portlets. One requirement of this approach is that the payload must implement the java.io.Serializable
			interface since it might be sent to a portlet in another WAR running in a different classloader.</para>
		<para>It could be argued that the Portlet 2.0 approaches for IPC have a common drawback in that they can lead to
			a potentially disruptive end-user experience. This is because they cause either an HTTP GET or HTTP POST
			which results in a full page refresh. Technologies such as ICEfaces Ajax Push can be used to solve this
			problem. Refer to the <link xlink:href="#ajaxpushipc">Ajax Push IPC</link> section of this document for more
			details. </para>
		<figure>
			<title>Illustration of Standard Portlet 2.0 IPC</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/ipc-standard.png" width="400px"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
